<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Climate change on Francesco Granella</title>
    <link>/tags/climate-change/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Climate change on Francesco Granella</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Francesco Granella {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/climate-change/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate Change Impacts on Within-Country Income Distributions</title>
      <link>/project/impacts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/impacts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eiee.org/member/martino-gilli/&#34;&gt;Martino Gilli&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.som.polimi.it/people/calcaterra-matteo-3/&#34;&gt;Matteo Calcaterra&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eiee.org/member/johannes-emmerling/&#34;&gt;Johannes Emmerling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper investigates the relationship between climate change and income inequality, recognizing that the economic impacts of climate change are not uniform across different levels of income within and across countries. Using methods from the existing literature on climate and economic growth, we analyze the economic impact of rising temperatures by within-country income decile. Our findings suggest that climate change disproportionately affects the poorer segments of the population within countries, even after accounting for a country&amp;rsquo;s ability to adapt to climate impacts, while the richest suffer the lowest damages. In a Reference scenario without additional climate action, we estimate that climate impacts could lead to an increase of the Gini index by up to six points, notably in Sub-Saharan Africa. Globally, we estimate that around three quarters of the total variation in climate impacts is due to between-country heterogeneity, and one-quarter is due to within-country inequality. We project damages to 2100 through the RICE50+ model and estimate the income elasticity of damages within countries. Our estimates indicate that the total economic impact of climate change is regressive, with an income elasticity of damages of 0.72 under our preferred specification. We find climate impacts to be especially regressive in poorer and hotter countries. While global damages are sensitive to the functional form of the damage function, the estimated income elasticity parameter is robust across different specifications.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Persistent Effect of Temperature on GDP identified from Lower Frequency Temperature Variability</title>
      <link>/project/tempgdp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/tempgdp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bastien-Olvera, B. A., Granella, F., &amp;amp; Moore, F. C. (2022). Persistent effect of temperature on GDP identified from lower frequency temperature variability. &lt;em&gt;Environmental Research Letters&lt;/em&gt;, 17(8), 084038&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is well established that temperature variability affects a range of outcomes relevant to human welfare, including health, emotion and mood, and productivity across a number of economic sectors. However, a critical and still unresolved empirical question is whether temperature variation has a long-lasting effect on economic productivity and, therefore, whether damages compound over time in response to long-lived changes in temperature expected with climate change. Several studies have identified a relationship between temperature and GDP, but empirical evidence as to the persistence of these effects is still weak. This paper presents a novel approach to isolate the persistent component of temperature effects on output using lower frequency temperature variation. The effects are heterogenous across countries but collectively, using three different GDP datasets, we find evidence of persistent effects, implying temperature affects the determinants of economic growth, not just economic productivity. This in turn means that the aggregate effects of climate change on GDP may be far larger and far more uncertain than currently represented in integrated assessment models used to calculate the social cost of carbon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
