<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Francesco Granella</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Francesco Granella</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Francesco Granella {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Unequal climate impacts on global values of natural capital</title>
      <link>/project/greenrice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/greenrice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Unequal climate impacts on global values of natural capital&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; (2023)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ecosystems generate a wide range of benefits for humans, including some market goods as well as other benefits that are not directly reflected in market activity1. Climate change will alter the distribution of ecosystems around the world and change the flow of these benefits2,3. However, the specific implications of ecosystem changes for human welfare remain unclear, as they depend on the nature of these changes, the value of the affected benefits and the extent to which communities rely on natural systems for their well-being4. Here we estimate country-level changes in economic production and the value of non-market ecosystem benefits resulting from climate-change-induced shifts in terrestrial vegetation cover, as projected by dynamic global vegetation models (DGVMs) driven by general circulation climate models. Our results show that the annual population-weighted mean global flow of non-market ecosystem benefits valued in the wealth accounts of the World Bank will be reduced by 9.2% in 2100 under the Shared Socioeconomic Pathway SSP2-6.0 with respect to the baseline no climate change scenario and that the global population-weighted average change in gross domestic product (GDP) by 2100 is −1.3% of the baseline GDP. Because lower-income countries are more reliant on natural capital, these GDP effects are regressive. Approximately 90% of these damages are borne by the poorest 50% of countries and regions, whereas the wealthiest 10% experience only 2% of these losses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The formation of secondary inorganic aerosols: A data-driven investigation of Lombardy&#39;s secondary inorganic aerosol problem</title>
      <link>/project/inhale/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/inhale/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eiee.org/member/stefania-renna/&#34;&gt;Stefania Renna&lt;/a&gt;and &lt;a href=&#34;https://laleluia.github.io/page/&#34;&gt;Lara Aleluia Reis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study performs a data-driven investigation of the impact of agriculture on air pollution in Lombardy, Italy, focusing on secondary inorganic particulate matter (PM) formation resulting from ammonia (NH3) emissions. Leveraging on the predictive power of machine learning models and exploiting the reduction in non-agricultural emissions during the 2020 COVID-19 lockdown, we analyze the complex relationship between NH3, nitrogen dioxide (NO2), and secondary inorganic aerosols (SIA). We find that even substantially large reduction in precursor emissions may not deliver large drops in secondary inorganic PM. While NO2 plays a significant role in urban environments, in rural areas where NH3 levels are high, both NO2 and NH3 contribute to SIA formation. This emphasizes the importance of considering both NH3 and NO2 emissions in policies controlling secondary inorganic PM, as reductions in both precursors may be necessary for significant improvements. The study provides insights into the interplay between agricultural practices and air pollution, more specifically the NH3–NO2 regime and its implications for effective air pollution control strategies in Lombardy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate Change Impacts on Within-Country Income Distributions</title>
      <link>/project/impacts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/impacts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eiee.org/member/martino-gilli/&#34;&gt;Martino Gilli&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.som.polimi.it/people/calcaterra-matteo-3/&#34;&gt;Matteo Calcaterra&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eiee.org/member/johannes-emmerling/&#34;&gt;Johannes Emmerling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper investigates the relationship between climate change and income inequality, recognizing that the economic impacts of climate change are not uniform across different levels of income within and across countries. Using methods from the existing literature on climate and economic growth, we analyze the economic impact of rising temperatures by within-country income decile. Our findings suggest that climate change disproportionately affects the poorer segments of the population within countries, even after accounting for a country&amp;rsquo;s ability to adapt to climate impacts, while the richest suffer the lowest damages. In a Reference scenario without additional climate action, we estimate that climate impacts could lead to an increase of the Gini index by up to six points, notably in Sub-Saharan Africa. Globally, we estimate that around three quarters of the total variation in climate impacts is due to between-country heterogeneity, and one-quarter is due to within-country inequality. We project damages to 2100 through the RICE50+ model and estimate the income elasticity of damages within countries. Our estimates indicate that the total economic impact of climate change is regressive, with an income elasticity of damages of 0.72 under our preferred specification. We find climate impacts to be especially regressive in poorer and hotter countries. While global damages are sensitive to the functional form of the damage function, the estimated income elasticity parameter is robust across different specifications.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CLAQC V1.0 – Country Level Air Quality Calculator. An Empirical Modeling Approach</title>
      <link>/project/claqc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/claqc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eiee.org/member/stefania-renna/&#34;&gt;Stefania Renna&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://laleluia.github.io/page/&#34;&gt;Lara Aleluia Reis&lt;/a&gt; and Paulina Estela Schulz-Antipa&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Country Level Air Quality Calculator (CLAQC) is an open-source modeling tool that utilizes national sectoral emissions and weather data to forecast monthly and annual concentrations PM2.5 and O3. CLAQC leverages the recent advancements in the CAMS system and employs CAMS global gridded emissions and CAMS reanalysis pollutant concentrations to improve the accuracy of its predictions. One of the notable strengths of CLAQC is its capability to provide country-specific and sectoral information. We have developed two methodological approaches, namely elastic net modeling and extreme gradient boosting regressor, that can effectively predict annual average concentrations for nearly all countries. However, we find that elastic net models have high variability in sectoral contributions. The tool can simulate a vast range of policy scenarios and can be integrated into national policy assessment and optimization frameworks. Finally, we present a method selection framework to optimize performance and an online tool displaying model results.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Persistent Effect of Temperature on GDP identified from Lower Frequency Temperature Variability</title>
      <link>/project/tempgdp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/tempgdp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bastien-Olvera, B. A., Granella, F., &amp;amp; Moore, F. C. (2022). Persistent effect of temperature on GDP identified from lower frequency temperature variability. &lt;em&gt;Environmental Research Letters&lt;/em&gt;, 17(8), 084038&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is well established that temperature variability affects a range of outcomes relevant to human welfare, including health, emotion and mood, and productivity across a number of economic sectors. However, a critical and still unresolved empirical question is whether temperature variation has a long-lasting effect on economic productivity and, therefore, whether damages compound over time in response to long-lived changes in temperature expected with climate change. Several studies have identified a relationship between temperature and GDP, but empirical evidence as to the persistence of these effects is still weak. This paper presents a novel approach to isolate the persistent component of temperature effects on output using lower frequency temperature variation. The effects are heterogenous across countries but collectively, using three different GDP datasets, we find evidence of persistent effects, implying temperature affects the determinants of economic growth, not just economic productivity. This in turn means that the aggregate effects of climate change on GDP may be far larger and far more uncertain than currently represented in integrated assessment models used to calculate the social cost of carbon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 lockdown only partially alleviates health impacts of air pollution in Northern Italy</title>
      <link>/project/covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/covid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Granella, F., Reis, L. A., Bosetti, V., &amp;amp; Tavoni, M. (2021). COVID-19 lockdown only partially alleviates health impacts of air pollution in Northern Italy. &lt;em&gt;Environmental Research Letters&lt;/em&gt;, 16(3), 035012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evaluating the reduction in pollution caused by a sudden change in emissions is complicated by the
confounding effect of weather variations. We propose an approach based on machine learning to
build counterfactual scenarios that address the effect of weather and apply it to the COVID-19
lockdown of Lombardy, Italy. We show that the lockdown reduced background concentrations of
PM2.5 by 3.84 µg m−3 (16%) and NO2 by 10.85 µg m−3 (33%). Improvement in air quality saved
at least 11% of the years of life lost and 19% of the premature deaths attributable to COVID-19 in
the region during the same period. The analysis highlights the benefits of improving air quality and
the need for an integrated policy response addressing the full diversity of emission sources.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heterogeneous Effects of Air Pollution on Physical Tasks: Evidence from Amateur Track and Field</title>
      <link>/project/track/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/track/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although a large share of the world’s population is employed in manual labor, our understanding of the productivity costs of air pollution for physically intensive work remains limited. This paper estimates the effect of fine particulate matter (PM 2.5) on purely physical tasks by analyzing half a million amateur track and field competition results, a setting where cognition plays a minor role. Exploiting the panel nature of the data and high dimensional fixed effects, I find that a 10 µg/m3 increase in PM 2.5 reduces performance by 1% of a standard deviation. The effect grows with the duration of effort, indicating that productivity losses may be larger for occupations requiring low-intensity and sustained effort, such as construction workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presentations: IAERE 2021, EAERE 2021, AERE@SEA 2021&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Campaign money for nothing? Understanding the consequences of a ban on corporate contributions: evidence from Brazil.</title>
      <link>/project/donations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/donations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We study the effects of the 2015 ban on corporate contributions in Brazil on the allocation of procurement contracts and the frequency of large personal contributions of corporate members, a channel to circumvent the ban. We use difference in differences regression models that compare outcomes of contributing and non-contributing firms before and after the ban. We document three findings. First, before the ban, contributing firms won 20 to 25% more procurement tenders per year than non-contributing firms. Second, the ban on corporate contributions significantly decreased the number of national procurement contracts won by contributing firms by 2 to 11 percentage points, a magnitude that only partially offset their previous advantage. Third, firms previously making large contributions circumvent the ban in both national and local elections with donations from owners and board members. Together, our findings suggest that a ban on corporate contributions have limited effects on the average influence of contributing firms when there are mechanisms to circumvent the ban.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presentations: MPSA 2020 (canceled), EPSA (2021), APSA (2020)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
