<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Air pollution on Francesco Granella</title>
    <link>/tags/air-pollution/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Air pollution on Francesco Granella</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Francesco Granella {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/air-pollution/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The formation of secondary inorganic aerosols: A data-driven investigation of Lombardy&#39;s secondary inorganic aerosol problem</title>
      <link>/project/inhale/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/inhale/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eiee.org/member/stefania-renna/&#34;&gt;Stefania Renna&lt;/a&gt;and &lt;a href=&#34;https://laleluia.github.io/page/&#34;&gt;Lara Aleluia Reis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study performs a data-driven investigation of the impact of agriculture on air pollution in Lombardy, Italy, focusing on secondary inorganic particulate matter (PM) formation resulting from ammonia (NH3) emissions. Leveraging on the predictive power of machine learning models and exploiting the reduction in non-agricultural emissions during the 2020 COVID-19 lockdown, we analyze the complex relationship between NH3, nitrogen dioxide (NO2), and secondary inorganic aerosols (SIA). We find that even substantially large reduction in precursor emissions may not deliver large drops in secondary inorganic PM. While NO2 plays a significant role in urban environments, in rural areas where NH3 levels are high, both NO2 and NH3 contribute to SIA formation. This emphasizes the importance of considering both NH3 and NO2 emissions in policies controlling secondary inorganic PM, as reductions in both precursors may be necessary for significant improvements. The study provides insights into the interplay between agricultural practices and air pollution, more specifically the NH3–NO2 regime and its implications for effective air pollution control strategies in Lombardy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 lockdown only partially alleviates health impacts of air pollution in Northern Italy</title>
      <link>/project/covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/covid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Granella, F., Reis, L. A., Bosetti, V., &amp;amp; Tavoni, M. (2021). COVID-19 lockdown only partially alleviates health impacts of air pollution in Northern Italy. &lt;em&gt;Environmental Research Letters&lt;/em&gt;, 16(3), 035012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evaluating the reduction in pollution caused by a sudden change in emissions is complicated by the
confounding effect of weather variations. We propose an approach based on machine learning to
build counterfactual scenarios that address the effect of weather and apply it to the COVID-19
lockdown of Lombardy, Italy. We show that the lockdown reduced background concentrations of
PM2.5 by 3.84 µg m−3 (16%) and NO2 by 10.85 µg m−3 (33%). Improvement in air quality saved
at least 11% of the years of life lost and 19% of the premature deaths attributable to COVID-19 in
the region during the same period. The analysis highlights the benefits of improving air quality and
the need for an integrated policy response addressing the full diversity of emission sources.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 lockdown only partially alleviates health impacts of air pollution in Northern Italy</title>
      <link>/publication/covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/covid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Published on &lt;em&gt;Environmental Research Letters&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Lara Aleluis Reis, Valentina Bosetti, and Massimo Tavoni.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evaluating the reduction in pollution caused by a sudden change in emissions is complicated by the confounding effect of weather variations. We propose an approach based on machine learning to build counterfactual scenarios that address the effect of weather and apply it to the COVID-19 lockdown of Lombardy, Italy. We show that the lockdown reduced background concentrations of PM2.5 by 3.84 µg m−3 (16%) and NO2 by 10.85 µg m−3 (33%). Improvement in air quality saved at least 11% of the years of life lost and 19% of the premature deaths attributable to COVID-19 in the region during the same period. The analysis highlights the benefits of improving air quality and the need for an integrated policy response addressing the full diversity of emission sources.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heterogeneous Effects of Air Pollution on Physical Tasks: Evidence from Amateur Track and Field</title>
      <link>/project/track/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/track/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although a large share of the world’s population is employed in manual labor, our understanding of the productivity costs of air pollution for physically intensive work remains limited. This paper estimates the effect of fine particulate matter (PM 2.5) on purely physical tasks by analyzing half a million amateur track and field competition results, a setting where cognition plays a minor role. Exploiting the panel nature of the data and high dimensional fixed effects, I find that a 10 µg/m3 increase in PM 2.5 reduces performance by 1% of a standard deviation. The effect grows with the duration of effort, indicating that productivity losses may be larger for occupations requiring low-intensity and sustained effort, such as construction workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presentations: IAERE 2021, EAERE 2021, AERE@SEA 2021&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
