<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on Francesco Granella</title>
    <link>/tags/publications/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on Francesco Granella</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Francesco Granella {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate Change Impacts on Within-Country Income Distributions</title>
      <link>/project/impacts/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/impacts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eiee.org/member/martino-gilli/&#34;&gt;Martino Gilli&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.som.polimi.it/people/calcaterra-matteo-3/&#34;&gt;Matteo Calcaterra&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eiee.org/member/johannes-emmerling/&#34;&gt;Johannes Emmerling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper investigates the relationship between climate change and income inequality, recognizing that the economic impacts of climate change are not uniform across different levels of income within and across countries. Using methods from the existing literature on climate and economic growth, we analyze the economic impact of rising temperatures by within-country income decile. Our findings suggest that climate change disproportionately affects the poorer segments of the population within countries, even after accounting for a country’s ability to adapt to climate impacts, while richer households suffer lower damages. In the reference scenario without additional climate action (3.6°C warming), we estimate that climate impacts could lead to an increase in the Gini index by up to six percentage points, notably in Sub-Saharan Africa. We project impacts to 2100 through the RICE50+ model and estimate the income elasticity of impacts within countries. Our estimates indicate that climate change damages are regressive, with an income elasticity of damages of 0.6 under our preferred specification. On the other hand, climate benefits are approximately income-neutral.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unequal climate impacts on global values of natural capital</title>
      <link>/project/greenrice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/greenrice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Unequal climate impacts on global values of natural capital&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; (2023)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ecosystems generate a wide range of benefits for humans, including some market goods as well as other benefits that are not directly reflected in market activity1. Climate change will alter the distribution of ecosystems around the world and change the flow of these benefits2,3. However, the specific implications of ecosystem changes for human welfare remain unclear, as they depend on the nature of these changes, the value of the affected benefits and the extent to which communities rely on natural systems for their well-being4. Here we estimate country-level changes in economic production and the value of non-market ecosystem benefits resulting from climate-change-induced shifts in terrestrial vegetation cover, as projected by dynamic global vegetation models (DGVMs) driven by general circulation climate models. Our results show that the annual population-weighted mean global flow of non-market ecosystem benefits valued in the wealth accounts of the World Bank will be reduced by 9.2% in 2100 under the Shared Socioeconomic Pathway SSP2-6.0 with respect to the baseline no climate change scenario and that the global population-weighted average change in gross domestic product (GDP) by 2100 is −1.3% of the baseline GDP. Because lower-income countries are more reliant on natural capital, these GDP effects are regressive. Approximately 90% of these damages are borne by the poorest 50% of countries and regions, whereas the wealthiest 10% experience only 2% of these losses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 lockdown only partially alleviates health impacts of air pollution in Northern Italy</title>
      <link>/project/covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/covid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Granella, F., Reis, L. A., Bosetti, V., &amp;amp; Tavoni, M. (2021). COVID-19 lockdown only partially alleviates health impacts of air pollution in Northern Italy. &lt;em&gt;Environmental Research Letters&lt;/em&gt;, 16(3), 035012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evaluating the reduction in pollution caused by a sudden change in emissions is complicated by the
confounding effect of weather variations. We propose an approach based on machine learning to
build counterfactual scenarios that address the effect of weather and apply it to the COVID-19
lockdown of Lombardy, Italy. We show that the lockdown reduced background concentrations of
PM2.5 by 3.84 µg m−3 (16%) and NO2 by 10.85 µg m−3 (33%). Improvement in air quality saved
at least 11% of the years of life lost and 19% of the premature deaths attributable to COVID-19 in
the region during the same period. The analysis highlights the benefits of improving air quality and
the need for an integrated policy response addressing the full diversity of emission sources.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 lockdown only partially alleviates health impacts of air pollution in Northern Italy</title>
      <link>/publication/covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/covid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Published on &lt;em&gt;Environmental Research Letters&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Lara Aleluis Reis, Valentina Bosetti, and Massimo Tavoni.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evaluating the reduction in pollution caused by a sudden change in emissions is complicated by the confounding effect of weather variations. We propose an approach based on machine learning to build counterfactual scenarios that address the effect of weather and apply it to the COVID-19 lockdown of Lombardy, Italy. We show that the lockdown reduced background concentrations of PM2.5 by 3.84 µg m−3 (16%) and NO2 by 10.85 µg m−3 (33%). Improvement in air quality saved at least 11% of the years of life lost and 19% of the premature deaths attributable to COVID-19 in the region during the same period. The analysis highlights the benefits of improving air quality and the need for an integrated policy response addressing the full diversity of emission sources.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
